Hi everyone, my name
is Dr. Matthew Heller.
I am a family and sports
medicine physician
and associate professor
over at NYITCOM,
College of
Osteopathic Medicine.
I have the honor of
presenting to you a
presentation on the abnormal
respiratory exam. This
is part of our DPR
lecture series. My email
address is over here in
case you all have any
questions, comments,
suggestions, concerns.
I'm always trying to make
my lectures better, so
if you have any ideas,
please let me know. I
hope you enjoyed my last
lecture. I believe it was
lecture number 91 with
the Cookie Monster. We
greatly appreciated being
a part of your lecture.
And if you have any
questions, let me know. This
might be my last lecture
for you all for the
class of 2027. Alright,
so for you guys, good luck
on rotation, I'm sure
you'll all be very well.
If you have any
questions, reach
out and we will
begin the lecture.
So again, just a
reminder, just fill out
the lecture feedback
form. Alright, if you
loved the lecture, if
you hated the lecture,
either way, I think it's always
good to get some feedback.
And the objectives today,
what we're going to talk
about mostly is talk about
the normal and abnormal breath
sound. We're going to talk
about what should be the
normal and what is abnormal
and when it's abnormal.
What is the differential
diagnosis and what do we
need to keep in mind as far
as treating the patient.
We're going to talk about
physical exam because
it's a DPR exercise,
so physical exam. We're
going to talk about the
history taken and the physical
exam, the how and why
we do the techniques.
We're going to talk about
normal breath sounds.
Normal breath sounds are
heard in normal places.
If you have normal
breath sounds heard in
abnormal places, it's
going to be an abnormal
exam. We'll go into
more detail later on.
We're going to recognize
the abnormal finding of the
thorax and the lungs. And
we're going to go through
some clinical scenarios. I
think clinical scenarios, I
think you'll all benefit
from them. We'll listen to
some lungs down, we're going
to have some fun. We're going
to make this a fun lecture
and hopefully, I know it
went a little over on the
last one, hopefully we can
make this a little before
whatever time frame is up.
And critical thinking into
a differential diagnosis.
So again, we are the
Red Wolves and the
Bears. So, um, hello
down to Johnville,
hello up to New York,
Long Island, um,
the Red Wolves and the Bears.
We will do a quick
roll call, so let me
change it over, get
out of the pen mode.
So if you are New
York and you're
the Bears, let
me hear you roar.
And if you're down south in
Joanville, let
me hear you howl.
To the FedEx presentation,
question of the day,
I'm just changing
the pen, I'm getting
back into the
pen mode, I got
the pen mode here.
So the FedEx question
of the day is how
many hours do you
see on this slide?
So if you count up all
the arrows that you see
on the slide, you might
be inclined to say,
I see 8.
1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8.
But one of the main
arrows that we don't see
is this arrow that we
see right there in FedEx.
Between the E and the X. And
that would be your ninth arrow.
So why do I even bring this
up? So first of all, now
every time you see a FedEx
truck, you're going to
be looking for that arrow.
But just know that that
arrow is always going
to lead you in the right
direction and it's always
going to lead you to success.
And that goes along with a
lot of the things that you do.
Sometimes you guys
are probably an extra
number 107, 108, 109
within that ballpark.
You study, you take an
exam, you study, you
take an exam, you
study, you take an exam.
Sometimes it can be easy
to lose that vision of
what you're looking for and
what you're working for.
So sometimes what
you're working for,
sometimes the arrow
might be a little hidden,
but eventually you
will find the arrow
and that's going to
lead you to succeed.
It's always going
to be there, but
sometimes you just
need to find it.
And this can be hard to
find, especially at 2 in
the morning and you have
exams coming up, and you
have so much to study,
you're behind the lectures,
behind the lab, right,
just think about the FedEx
and I'm sure that will
lead you to the right path.
So when I first started
the lecture and I
first started with this
FedEx introduction,
right, I was actually
walking down New York City,
right, on my way to a fight
night on on Broad Street
and then I saw a FedEx
truck and I just started
looking at that FedEx truck
and I was looking at the
hour and I'm like how can
I incorporate that into
a Lexer how cool would that
be right and then I got
somebody approached me
from behind and it was a
FedEx driver and I just
asked me like what are you
doing and I'm like first nice
truck and um then I asked
him to take a picture of
me with the truck and he
was a little confused but
he did take the picture
And then I told him
why we were taking the
pictures, so it wasn't
going to be so awkward.
And we stayed in contact,
and when I gave the
lectures to FedEx Introduction
a few years ago, he
was like, hey FedEx guys,
I can't sleep, I'm excited
for the lecture, thank you
for taking the picture.
And he's like, 3 or 5
a.m., please go to bed.
And then I'm like, remember
the message I wanted
to give the students,
and he was like, always
move forward, keep moving,
keep moving forward.
So always find the arrow
that's going to lead
you to seed, and it's
always going to be there
every time you see a FedEx
truck. Just remember that
the arrow is pointing
in the right direction.
And just like FedEx,
you will all get to
your destination in
your medical career.
We all have a destination.
We're all going to
get there, right? Some
of you will end up in
different places in the
medical field, different
specialties, different
hospitals, some will
go far, some are going
to stay local, and
you're going to end up
in a different program.
And whether you get there
by train or plane or by
cars, some of you will walk
there if you had no other
way, but eventually you all
get to your destination.
There will be many
times that you guys
feel on your
journey that you're
feeling like you're
hanging off a cliff.
And there will be
many times where you
feel like he just can't
get off the ground.
There will be many
times when you feel
like the roads are
a little slippery.
And some of you might even
find yourself upside down.
Some of you may get
sidetracked and get
completely off the
road, right, but
eventually you'll make
it back onto the road.
Some of you will find
an uphill battle.
Some of you at some point
will feel like it burns out.
And some of you will feel
like you're all alone.
But at the end of
the journey you
will all get to
your destination.
And some of you will go far,
some of you will stay near.
Some Some of you
may end up right
back here, like
this guy right here.
And along the way,
you guys are going
to help others, right, here's a
FedEx, whether your
FedEx or your UPS.
Just never forget where
it all began, right here
at NYT, whether it was
down in Jonesville or up in
Long Island and a quick
disclosure statement I do
have no affiliation official
affiliation with FedEx
and there is no real or
parent conflict of interest
related to the content
of this introduction
presentation and I do not get
to send any free deliveries
but FedEx will get 400
plus medical students
looking for their arrow every
time that they see their
logo and And maybe I'll
put them in a hashtag in
a future post, FedEx,
hashtag, thank you, FedEx.
So we will move on to
something more exciting.
We're going to talk about
the lungs, and we're going
to talk about the basic
anatomy of the lungs.
So when you do your
physical exam and you're
listening, you're
palpating, you know what
you're palpating, what
you're listening to right
underneath the area
that you're assessing.
You should be able to get
a general idea of which
lobe you're examining,
whether you're listening from
the front or you're
listening from the back, or
anterior or posterior, to
use medical terminology.
On the anterior view,
right, your right lung,
in the anterior view,
right, you can see that the
right upper lobe and right
middle lobe is more prominent
and the right lower lobe
you might not be able to
see as well or listen to as
well. so that's why we do
these exam anteriorly and
we do the exam posteriorly.
Right lung do have
three lobes and
the left lung do
have two lobes.
On the posterior view,
right, you can kind
of see that the
right middle lobe is
difficult to assess
because you might only
get a little bit of a
portion right there.
Again, left upper
lobe, left lower lobe.
Right upper and right lower.
You want to make sure
you're listening,
you're palpating in all
of these lung fields.
And we have the lateral view.
On the right side, you
can see that you have
probably better access
to all three lung
fields, the right
upper, middle, and lower
lobe. And notice again
that you're not able
to get a good examination,
unless you do anterior
and posterior at minimal,
right? And then you can
also listen to the lateral
view if you need to.
A very, very quick
brief review, the
trachea, we know
that it's midline.
That goes into the
primary bronchi at the
sternal angle, so that's
going to break into
the left and the right
main stem bronchi.
And from the posterior
view, right, some
people will say that this
is about the T4 area,
right, about the T3,
T5, right, I'm not
going to question you
on that at all, but
just know that the
approximate area is on
both the anterior and
the posterior side.
When a patient comes in with
a respiratory complaint,
right, we have to do a
health history, We always
do an HPI, History of
Present Illness, and we're
going to look at the common
and concerning symptoms.
So some very common
complaints, somebody comes in
with chest pain, somebody
comes in with shortness of
breath, they're wheezing,
they cough, they're coughing
up blood, they have daytime
sleepiness or snoring or
any kind of disorders,
sleeping or abnormal sleep.
A patient with chest pain, the
differential diagnosis
is very, very broad.
And it's up to us to
really investigate
what is the chest
pain coming from.
The patient,
by their presentation,
by the history, by
the physical exam,
you're going to have
a general idea of
being able to narrow it
down to what's the
most likely diagnosis.
And sometimes you have
to ask the question, are
you having chest pain
that's coming with shortness
of breath, or are you
having shortness of
breath that's coming with
chest pain? And that can
lead to two different,
differential diagnoses.
Some cardiac causes,
right, you always want to
wear antonyme, myocardial
infarction, pericarditis,
aortic dissection,
right, these are the more
serious cardiac causes
you have to make sure
the patient is not
having, right, before you
diagnose somebody with
a less severe diagnosis.
And sometimes it's not
going to be what the patient
is saying, sometimes you
can just look at the patient
and see how are they
describing the pain right with
their hand right sometimes
they'll take a clenched
fist and they'll put it
over their sternum and that
could be suggestive of
possibly a cardiac etiology or
they might take one finger
and they might point to
one tender spot on the
chest wall and that will be
suggestive more muscular
skeletal pain or they might
have their hand moving from
the neck to the epigathrium
and they might be moving
their hand up and down
right, and that could be
suggested more for heartburn.
So chest pain can also
have some pulmonary
causes, right, pleuritic
chest pain is a very sharp
and sudden pain, almost
like a stabbing pain
that's worse with deep
inspiration and that's
based off inflammation
of the parietal pleur.
You can also have some GI
causes, so cardiac pulmonary,
we have GI causes, we
could think about reflux,
reflux on diffuse
esophageal spasm which is
basically a motor dysfunction
of the esophageal muscle
and that could be
aggravated by swallowing
of food or any kind of
cold or cool liquid.
GI and then we have
muscular skeletal complaints
right whether it's chest
wall pain or costochondritis
and costochondritis
inflammation of the
of the of the
cartilage of the costal
cartilage And then we have
psychiatric etiologies
such as anxiety
and panic disorder.
Another common and
potentially concerning
pulmonary complaint is
short of the breath.
And this is basically
a pain list, but it's
an uncomfortable awareness
of the breathing.
You can ask the patient, have
you had any
difficulty breathing?
and if the symptoms occur
when they're at rest
or are they occurring
when they're exercising,
moving around.
And then if they do have
pain on exercise, you
can say how much exercise,
how much exertion are
you moving before the
shortness of breath occurs.
And some patients
would say, Doc, I get
short of breath just
walking up the step.
That might be a little
bit more severe,
or somebody that said, Doc,
I get shortness of breath
after I walk 10 city
blocks. I used to be able to
walk 40 city blocks, now I
can't even barely make 10.
So now you know what
their baseline is, and now
you know what they're
limited to at this point.
There's no absolute
scale for quantifying
shortness of breath. So
when we talk about pain,
back in the spring, we
talked a lot about pain.
My lecture is for the hip,
For the knee, the ankle,
right, patients came
in with pain, we asked
them how bad is the
pain on a scale of 1
to 10. And when we talk
about soreness of breath,
there is no severity,
right, so there's no
similar scale. So what we
do to determine the
severity is based on the
activities of daily living
and what were they able
to do before and what
are they able to do now.
As I mentioned before,
they used to be
able to walk 40 blocks
in New York City
or in Jonesville, and
now they can only walk
10, right. So now we
know the baseline, we
know what they're
limited to at this point.
Another common complaint is a
patient is going
to have a cough,
right?
Very, very, very commonly
seen in the office.
And what is a cough?
A cough is a reflex
response to a stimuli
that irritates receptors
in the larynx, trachea,
and large bronchi.
This could be a variety of
stimuli, right?
Whether it's mucus,
pus, blood, it
could be an external
agent, such as any
kind of allergen.
People have allergies, a
pollen, or whatever it might
be. It could be the air,
the cold air, hot air,
any foreign body. That might
trigger a cough or dust.
Anything that's
externally into the body,
that could be a trigger
for a cough. Then we
have some other causes
that include inflammation
of the respiratory
mucosa, pneumonia,
pulmonary edema,
any kind of tumor,
or enlarged peribronchial
lymph nodes.
And then cardiac
causes can also cause
a cough as well,
more commonly we see
this with congestive
heart failure.
A cough can be divided
into acute and it
could be subacute or
it could be chronic.
These numbers, they
can fluctuate based on
different resources,
so don't get caught up
thinking acute is less
than three weeks. Some
people say acute
will be less than two
weeks, and then subacute
is two to four weeks.
The most common cause of
an acute crop is an acute
viral upper
respiratory infection.
Other causes can include
bronchitis, pneumonia,
left-sided heart failure,
asthma, foreign body,
smoking, ACE inhibitor, right,
one of the main side effects
that could come from an
ACE inhibitor is an acute
cough. So you can ask them,
have you began any new
medication? And I'll tell
you, doc, I just took an
ACE inhibitor, I started two
weeks ago, right, I started
taking it from my high
blood pressure. All right,
so here we talk about high
blood pressure but the
medication is having a side
effect of a cough, right?
Subacute, right, sometimes
people get over the
infection but they have
that lingering cough that
just doesn't want to go
away, right? That nagging
cough just keep going,
right? We keep that in the
differential diagnosis,
pertussis, reflux, asthma,
bacterial sinusitis,
and then in the more
chronic we think about post
-nasal drip, right, whether
it's from allergies or
any other diagnosis,
asthma, reflux, chronic
bronchitis, bronchiectasis,
right, so you can see
a cough is one symptom,
but it can have many, many
different differential
diagnosis.
So when a patient comes in
and they say, Doc, I have
a cough, right, we want to
know some other questions
about the cough, right,
this is real stuff that's
not part of your PQRST,
but it should be a part of
your HPI, right. You should
be able to document a
patient has a non-productive
crop or the patient has
a productive crop, cropping
up phlegm, right. What
color is the phlegm? How
much of the phlegm? Well,
any other sputum that's
coming out, the consistency,
right. So here we talk about
color, odor, consistency
of the sputum, mucoid sputum
is usually more common in
a viral infection or specific
fibrosis, or you can have
a prevalent sputum, right?
A more thick colored sputum
and that's usually more
for bacteria and pneumonia.
All right, so again,
more like translucent
white type of sputum versus
more thick. And let the
patient describe it to
you because they will
probably do a better job
describing it and let them
describe it in their own
words. So don't put the
words in their mouth by
asking them, Is it green?
Is it red? Is it yellow?
Let the patient describe how
they feel it's coming out.
And then the quantity, right?
How much do you think you're
coughing up in
the last 24 hours?
And the tech book would say,
describe it as a teaspoon,
a tablespoon, a quarter
of a cup. But I can
tell you, in practice, no
patient ever came to me and
told me that they coughed
up a teaspoon of sputum.
What they usually say,
Doc, I'm cropping up
a lot of sputum every
day for the last
three days. Or they'll
say, I'm cropping up a
little sputum. So a
lot, a little, medium.
They're going to
say it in their own
words. Let them say
it in their own words.
Hemopysis is cropping up blood.
And that's usually from the
lower respiratory tract.
You want to quantify the
volume of the blood produced.
right the setting the
activities associated
symptoms and the blood could
be anywhere from like blood
streaks bruntum or it
could be like a frank blood
very very bright red blood
you need to quantify again
the setting activities
and confirm is it really
coughing up blood or the
patient vomiting blood now
if the patient is coughing
up blood chances are coming
from the respiratory
tract if the patient is
vomiting blood right probably
coming from the GI tract
Daytime sleepiness,
snoring, disordered
sleep, this is another
common pulmonary
complaint that we will
see in the office.
The patient may
report excessive
daytime sleepiness and fatigue.
They may act about, we can
act about problems that
they have, maybe they're
snoring, maybe they have
any witness apnea when
they're sleeping, any
awakening. Maybe they're
waking up and they have a
choking sensation or they
have a morning headache.
You want to
consider any kind of
obstructive sleep
apnea, which is commonly
seen in patients
that are obese.
They have treatment
-resistant hypertension,
any joy issue,
posterior malocclusion,
heart barrier,
afib, stroke, type 2 diabetes.
And these diagnoses
can all be a higher
risk for, create
a higher risk for
patients to have
obstructive sleep apnea.
A mechanism of daytime
sleepiness or snoring
can be inability of the
brain stem respiratory
center, disordered sleep
arousal, disordered
contraction of the upper
airway muscles, right,
denioglossal malfunction
and anatomical changes
contributing to airway
collapse such as obesity.
All right, so you go
through the history, you go
through your HPI and you
get a good history from
the patient. You have an
idea what could be leading
to their symptoms and
next thing we're going
to do, we're going to go
into the physical exam.
All right, so you get your
full history, you summarize
the interviews of the
patient, you're going to begin
the physical exam, and
you're going to start out
with the vital signs. So in
respiratory, the vital signs
we're looking for is,
well, we're looking at all
the vital signs, but the
pulmonary is the respiratory.
You're looking at
the respiratory rate.
Then we're going to talk about
inspection,
palpation, percussion,
altercation, and any
additional examination skills.
Right, fremitus,
agophony, whispered
pectoralis, and bronchopony.
Respiratory rate and
rhythm, right, so
it's not just looking
at their rate, it's
looking at the rhythm
of their breathing.
So normal in an adult is
14 to 20, right, kids and
younger infants can just
breathe a little quicker,
right, so they're breathing
44 breaths per minute.
If an adult was
breathing 24-4 breaths
per minute, that
would be not good.
That would be
insufficient probably.
But for an infant, that
could be their normal.
Anybody that's breathing
a little bit slower is
going to be bradypnea,
bradypnea, slow breathing.
And that could be due
to abnormal alveolar
hypoventilation. That could
be without increased tidal
volume. And that could be
from a number of reasons,
whether we have increased
intracranial pressure, head
trauma, any drug-induced
respiratory depressants,
opiate overdose, uremia,
sighing respiration.
Sigh in respiration is
breathing punctuated by
frequent sighs, suggests
hyperventilation syndrome, and
that's the common cause
of dyspnea and dizziness.
We're all going to
sigh once in a while.
That doesn't mean it's
anything pathologic.
But if it's very, very
frequent, that could
mean that there's some
underlying pathology.
And again, that can also lead
to diphnia and dizziness.
So we had breathe hypnea,
now we have tachypnea.
That's basically rapid,
shallow breathing.
So there's a lot of
different causes, and
that could be due to
salicylate intoxication,
respiratory lung
disease, pleuritic
chest pain, and an
elevated diaphragm.
There's chain stroke
breathing. So all
these different
rhythms of breathing.
So it's not always
about the rate,
it's about the rhythm as well.
So we're talking
about chain stroke
breathing, that period
of deep breathing
alternate with period of apnea.
Apnea is no breathing or
not breathing. We also have
obstructive breathing, some
of you may have grew up with
the diagnosis of asthma
or maybe you knew somebody
with COPD, these are all
obstructive breathing and that's
where your expiration is
prolonged due to narrowed
airways. The airway is going
to get narrow and you're
going to be forcing the air
to get out. And that's usually
more common in asthma and
COPD, chronic bronchitis.
Then we have rapid deep
breathing, that's hypersnea.
So we do this all the time,
we see this a lot, well at
least I rapid deep breathe
when I exercise at the
Tuesday morning Fit Physician
run, right, after running
with the medical students,
trying to keep up with them,
right, I may finish and I'll
be in a rapid deep breathing
phase, right, because
I am trying to meet my
metabolic demand, trying to
get the oxygen to the muscles.
You can also go into rapid deep
breathing when you go
into high altitude,
sepsis, anemia, and then
there's hyperventilation,
right, and that's independent
of metabolic demand,
right, so hyperpnea, rapid
deep breathing is due
to metabolic demand, and then
you have hyperventilation,
right, which is independent
of metabolic demand,
except if a patient is
in respiratory acidosis.
They're going to feel
lightheaded and tangling
that may arise from a
decrease in CO2 concentration.
Because you're going
to be breathing so
fast, you're going to be
blowing off all the CO2.
Then we have Kohl's
-Mal breathing, another
pattern of breathing,
Kohl's-Mal breathing.
Compensatory over
-breathing, over-breathing
due to systemic
acidosis. This is where
we're going to see
this in patients that
have DKA, which is
diabetic ketoacidosis.
Kohl's-Mal respiration. And
then we will have atoxic
breathing, or biot
breathing, which is irregular
breathing where they have
periods of apnea, meaning they're
not breathing, and then
they alternate with regular
deep breath with not
suddenly for short interval.
Causes of this
include meningitis,
respiratory depression,
and brain injury,
typically at the
medullary level.
So we see a lot of different
patterns of breathing,
so it's not always
about the rate. right,
you want to notice any
abnormal pattern, right,
that could be part of an
abnormal physical exam.
Any signs of respiratory
distress, right, this is
why we always talk about
general impresses, right,
looking at the patient,
right, you're going to
assess the respiratory rate,
you're going to inspect
the patient's color for
cyanosis or pallor, you're
going to listen for any
audible sound or breathing,
sometime before you
even enter the room, you
can hear the patient
breathing in an abnormal way,
or you can hear them from
the waiting room, right,
that the patient is
breathing in an abnormal way.
You're going to look for
the neck, look at the
neck for contraction of
the accessory muscles.
So accessory muscle use
is not a good thing.
Usually you should
just be using the
diaphragm for breathing,
but sometimes if
you're using intercostal
muscles, you're using
your neck muscles,
this is all a sign that
you might be in a
little bit of distress.
Other signs of respiratory
distress is tripodting
or pursing at the lip. So
you go in and they have
their hands in front of
them and they're leaning
forward trying to get a
better breath in. Or they
might be pursing their
lips trying to be able
to get that breathing,
trying to get the air out.
And then you might have a case
where trachea
might be displaced.
Lateral displacement of
the trachea can occur
in pneumothorax or in
any pleural infusion.
So you get that
general impression
of the patient and
now we're going to
begin with inspection
of the chest.
So inspection always
begins with looking at the
shape of the chest and
how this how the chest
moves right. So we're
going to start out with
the shape right. So
everything I have listed
here is the shape right.
So they could have pexis
equitatum or they can
have pexis carinatum.
Equitatum, right,
thing of cave,
right, where the
chest is caving in.
Pigeon chest or pexis
carinatum, right, they're
going to have the chest
coming all the way out
and come back in, right,
and that's going to
make it look like the
chest is more anteriorly.
Then we have the bowel
chest. We might have a
traumatic flail chest and
thoracic hyposcoliosis.
Again, this is all shape
of the of the chest.
Pictures sometimes helps
a lot better. So in
a normal adult, right,
the lateral diameter of
the thoracic is greater
than its AP diameter.
And so we have a normal
adult, which is right
here, and we're going
to know that the lateral
diameter is going to
be greater than the AP
And the ratio is usually
going to be up to 0.7
to about 0.9 and that
goes up as we get older.
A patient that has a
history of smoking and they
have a history of COPD,
we kind of lose that
to how now the AP diameter
is even bigger than it
was up here. right, so
that is an example of
bowel chest, right, that's
usually seen in COPD.
A patient with pexis
activatum, again pexis
activatum, right, the
chest is going to cave
in, right, here we see
the chest caving in.
And pexis carinatum,
right, carinatum, pigeon
chest, you're going
to see that the chest
comes out and then it
goes back down. And
here we kind of see
that the chest comes
out and then some back.
So you have an anteriorly
displaced sternum.
So a pectus carinatum,
also known as pigeon chest.
I think that's a pigeon.
But you can see the
deformity, and here we have
that similar deformity.
The sternum is
displaced, anteriorly
increasing the AP diameter.
This is not necessarily
always a surgical case,
this is not always a
surgical case that needs
to be done, but sometimes
they will do surgery
on a young kid as more
of a cosmetic issue.
If somebody goes to a
birthday party at nine years
old and they're afraid
to take off their shirt
and they're embarrassed,
it could be something
that the surgeon considers,
the pediatric surgeon
considers, the orthopediatric
surgeon will consider,
and they'll do this more
for cosmetic reasons.
What could be more dangerous
sometimes is the pexis
excavetum, right, pexis
excavetum. This is more
dangerous because this might
impact the cardiac output,
this might impact the lung
capacity, and the cardiothoracic
structure underneath. So
we want to keep an eye
on the patients that have
a pexis excavetum. Is it
going to completely limit
their ability to compete?
And I think this
guy gives you a good
example, and the
answer to that is no.
So this is Cody Miller,
this is from the
Olympic swimmer, and
he's in the Olympics.
So basically, the question
I ask is, is it going
to limit you in your
physical activities? probably
not but it has the
potential to impact your
cardiac output and decrease
your lung capacity.
We talked about the traumatic
flare test right so you
might have a patient that
have multiple rib fractures
right and that's going to
cause paradoxical movements
of the thorax okay so
normally when you breathe in
on inspiration right this
red line should really be
out here and then when you
breathe out, it goes down.
But in the traumatic
flare test,
they broke a couple of ribs.
It's going to go in a
paradoxical movement.
And then we have, finally, we
have the abnormal
spine curvature,
right?
The vertebra is rotating
with the deformity of the
chest, and that is your
thoracic hyposcoliosis.
You can kind of see the
spine convexity, right?
Convexity is going to
be true to the right.
It's convexity
versus concavity.
Concavity, think
about the cave.
It's going to look
like a cave. Convexity,
you're going to kind of
see how it's coming out.
And then on the right
side, the ribs are
going to widely be
separated, and on the left
side, the ribs are
going to close together.
So all that went into the
shape of the chest, And now
we are going to discuss
the movement of the chest.
You are going to be
looking for deformities
or asymmetry when
the chest expands.
You might have abnormal
muscle retractions
of the intercostal spaces
during inspiration.
Impaired respiratory movements
on one or both sides.
Or you might have a
unilateral leg in movement.
And so in fact, now
we are going to begin
palpations. Focus on
areas of tenderness or
bruising or respiratory
expansion and fremitus.
So identify, you don't want
to look for any kind of
tenderness area, right?
Notice where tender and
you're going to feel is it
coming on the bone and are
you getting any kind of
bone step off, right? So if
they took a lot of hits
to the rib or they're in a
accident, they're in, I
checked for this after an MMA
fight, the fighter comes
out, I'm going to palpate
their rib, I'm going to
make sure they don't have
any bone step off or any
issues, right? that might be
for consideration for
potentially a fractured rib.
I'm going to evaluate
the chest expansion by
placing my thumb over
the level of the 10th rib
and loosely graphing
parallel to the lateral
ribcage and having the
patient take a deep breath
deep breath in and
feeling how the
ribcage is expanding
and is contracting.
I'm going to palpate
both lungs for
symmetric tactile fremitus.
Right, so fremitus
is more of a vibration
that's palpable,
right, so it's a palpable
vibration that's transmitted
through the bronchopulmonary
tree to the chest wall.
So here's an example of
how patients, right, so
a patient comes out and
what I mentioned before,
you kind of grab at the
10th, about the 10th
rib and the hand goes
out laterally and you're
going to have the patient
take a deep breath in.
Some abnormal findings to
look for in the freminus
is going to be either
decreased or it's increased.
You're going to
notice that there's
decreased freminus
in condition,
in condition where
the air is trapped
in the lung space
such as COPD,
asthma, and alexuses.
So air is trapped is going
to be one way to decrease
your freminus and then
when you have increase in
the space between the lung
and the chest wall, and
that's due to pneumothorax
or pleural effusions.
You're going to notice
an increase in freminus
when there's a solid
or fluid that's found
in the lung, consolidation
or some tumors.
Again, you're looking
for symmetry, right,
asymmetric increased
freminus, meaning you're
going to have increased
freminus on one side.
That's usually due to some kind
of consolidation in the tissue.
After palpate, we move
on to percussion and that
produces audible sound and
palpable vibrations. That's
going to help you establish
where the underlying
tissue is air filled or
fluid filled or consolidated.
So the key thing to
know here is that the
healthy lungs are resonant.
The healthy lungs are
resonant when it's dull,
right, it's usually not good.
Fluid or solid tissue
will place in an air
containing lung or
occupy the pleural space
beneath your percussing
finger, right. So an
example might be pneumonia
or pleural effusions.
One thing to know
is that percussions,
right, will
penetrate about five
to seven centimeters
into the chest.
However, it's not going to
aid in the detection of a
lesion that's deep within
the chest, right? But if it's
more superficial within
five to seven centimeters,
right, you might
be able to detect
some kind of lesion
or consolidations.
You want to make sure
you do this bilaterally.
And again, healthy
lungs are resonant,
right? But what if you
have too much resonant,
right? Does that
mean it's healthy?
Probably they're not.
There might be an issue
with retaining too
much air, such as COPD
or asthma. If it's
unilateral, it usually
suggests that there's a
large pneumothrack or
an air-filled bulla.
And then the opposite
of hyper-resinant, if
it's dull, so we talked
about dullness, identify
that there might be
something on the line.
So what we can do here is
we can identify the descent
of the diaphragm or
diaphragmatic excursion. So
we're going to begin
percussing above the expected
level of dullness, so within
the lung cavity. We're
going to palpate, we're
going to percuss and we're
going to feel resident.
And what we're going to
do, we're going to work
our way down until we don't
feel resident anymore and
then we feel dullness.
And what that's going to
tell us is that that's going
to confirm, that's going
to tell us the descent
of the diaphragm or the
diaphragmatic exertion. So
what do I mean by what I
just said? So basically we're
going to work up here and
you should feel resonant
and as you work your way
down, right, you're going to
get to an area where it's
going to turn into a dull,
right. If you do
one side and this is
the area and you
do another side and
this is the area
where it changes over,
right, you might have,
This is an abnormally high
level of exertion, so what
this is going to suggest
is that there might be
a pleural effusion or an
elevated hemidiaphragm,
because this is the area
where you go from resonant
to dull, right over here.
Again, by differentiating
between dullness and
resonant, you're able to
estimate the extent of the
diaphragmatic exertion,
and And by determining the
distance between the level of
dullness on full expiration
and the level of dullness
on full expiration,
right? And what's normal
should be about 3 to 5.5.
So again, determine the
distance between the
level of dullness on
full expiration and
the level of dullness
on full expiration. And
you should get about
3 to 5.5 centimeters.
Is it going to be
exact? Probably not,
right? But it should be
within that ballpark.
You're done with
percussions, oscillations,
right, you're going
to set the airflow
through the tracheal
bronchial tree.
Listening to the sound
generated by breathing, right,
so listening to the sound
by normal breathing. And
then you're going to be
listening for any adventitious,
right. Adventitious is a
very fancy way to say added,
right. There's some sound
that should never be there,
right, and if you hear
it, then it's usually not
a good thing. It's usually
some kind of pathology.
And then observation, we'll
talk later on about the
abnormality, right, you can
also do some extra testing,
such as using a patient's
spoken or whispered word or
voice as they are transmitted
through the chest wall.
So the breath sound may
be decreased, right, so
when airflow is decreased,
the breath sound is
going to be decreased,
right. So that's usually
done in any kind of
obstructive lung disease,
COPD, asthma, or any kind
of respiratory muscle
weakness is going to decrease
the breath sound. And
also, you're going to
have decreased breath
sound when the transmission
of the sound is poor.
So pleurifusion,
pneumothorax, COPD, right?
So COPD actually could
be both categories, but
when the transmission
of the sound is poor,
you're going to have a
decreased breath sound.
um you're going to be
listening for normal breath
sounds of the lungs
right vesicular is going
to be predominant right
you should hear vesicular
breath sounds throughout
the entire lung field
or for most of the
lung field right
some other breath
sounds that are normal
uh bronchovesicular with an
inspiratory and expiratory
sound at equal length
um you're going to have
the bronchial breath sound
with the louder harsher
and higher and **** with
a short silence, and then
you're going to have the
tracheal breath sounds.
So these are all
normal breath sounds
as long as they're
in a normal place.
So normal breath sounds in
a normal place is a normal
exam, but if you have a
normal breath sound in
an abnormal place, then
you're going to suspect some
kind of bronchopathology.
So for example, if you
have bronchovascular or
bronchial breath sounds in
an abnormal place so if
you hear predominantly
bronchial vesicular or
bronchial breath sound where you
should really be hearing
the vesicular right you
might it might suggest that
there's some replacement
of the air-filled lung
by fluid or consolidation
so again normal and a normal
is normal normal breath
sound in an abnormal area
is going to be abnormal
So, we like to listen to
some actual sounds, so I
am getting out of the pen
mode, and we are going to
take a quick listen to
our tracheal breath sound.
Tickler breath
sound, which is what
we should hear over
most of the lungs.
Bronchial breath sound.
Alright, this is heard
mostly over the manubrium.
Broncovesicular breath
down, which is heard mostly
in the first and second
interspaces anteriorly. Go
back into the pen mode.
Point here, pen.
Alright, so again, vesicular is
heard over most
of the lung field.
All these others are
heard in a specific
area, but if you hear
them in an abnormal place,
then it's abnormal
physical exam finding
and you would want to
further investigate.
So here we kind of
talk vesicular again
most of the lung
field is all vesicular
and then we have the
other normal breath
sound as long as it's
over a normal area.
So breath sounds are
predominantly vesicular
right but then you have
other areas where it
It might be bronchial
or bronchovecicular.
If this is over, if you hear
these breaths down in an
area where you normally hear
vesicular, you might know
that there's some pathology
to it, and then you can
do some transmitted voice
sounds. You can do the
egophony test, bronchophony,
or the whispers pectoralis.
You might even have
some increased tactile
femminus, and then in the
dull lung of the pleural
effusion, breath sounds
are decreased or absent.
And the transmitted
voice sound we're
going to hear in
just a little bit.
Abnormal breath sounds.
So if they have absence
or decreased breath
sounds, you're going to
be thinking about
pathology. You're going to
be thinking about COPD,
emphysema, pleural
effusion, normal stomach,
asthma, all potential.
Bronchial breath
sounds in an abnormal
location. I've
said that so many
times because it's
important to know.
indicate that there's
area of consolidation and
you may want to further
test your suspicions.
Um so we talked about
the breath sound now
we're going to talk
about adventitious which
is a fancy way to say
added breath sound right
so something that
should not be there ever
right so crackles right
we don't want to hear
crackles uh that result
from a series of tiny
explosions from when the
small distal airways deflated
during expiration pop
open during inspirations.
It's a very
discontinuous sound and
it heard mostly
on inspirations.
I'm not going to expect you
to know or to be able to
differentiate between fine
and coarse because there's
so many overlap between
the two, but just know that
even crackles can be broken
down into fine and coarse.
Fine is described
more as a um as like
you're taking a
piece of hair between
your fingers close
to your ears.
That was just coarse
crackles which is more for
like velcro fastener. It
sounds more like a velcro.
Wheezing very common right
sometimes you don't even
need to put the stethoscope
on the patient you
can just hear them breathing
and you hear a very very
high-pitched sound and
that's usually a sign that
maybe they have asthma
or some other obstructive
airway disease. That's a
continuous musical sound
that occurs during rapid
airflow through the bronchial
airways that are narrowed
and here we'll play.
normal
lung sounds or added breath
sounds that are abnormal
right um usually that
will help you in your
differential diagnosis all
right next we're going to
talk about ronchi which is
the uh secretion that you
have in the largest airway
right considered to be
a variant of wheezes They
might have some similarities,
some overlap, and here
we have some ronchi.
So, if you hear something
like that, you might hear
secretion, right,
sometimes it can actually
disappear if you have the
pacing corp, right, so if
you have the pacing corp
a couple of they might be
able to get rid of that
secretion, right, and then
you might hear a normal
breath sound afterwards.
So if you hear something
like that, just
know that there could
be secretion, have
them call up, and re
-list and re-evaluate.
Next is going to be Strider,
right? Strider is another
added breath sound, right?
This is not good. This
is a sound that if you
hear them in the waiting
room, you're going to want
to not keep them waiting
any longer, and you're
going to bring them in the
office and make sure that
you treat them appropriately.
This is a sign of respiratory
distress. This can
be heard without a stethoscope
again so you don't even
need to be near them and
you you could probably
hear this once you hear
it the first time when you
guys are on rotation. That
is something that you're
never going to forget and
I will show you the sound.
All right, so that's
not a good sound,
right? That's a sound
that did some kind of
partial obstruction
of the upper airway.
Okay, and then on the final
one of the added breath
sounds we're going to talk
about is the pleural rub.
It's
caused by inflamed
viscous pleural surfaces
as it slides across
the parietal pleura.
Very, very discontinuous.
It's not musical at
all. At least it doesn't
sound musical at all.
I heard during inspiration
and expiration.
Then some of, if not all,
of the following tests can
be performed if there's
an index of suspicion. So
if you think anybody has
consolidation, you can do one
of these three testing,
bronchopony, eophony,
whispered pectorility. In DPR
lab, we're going to do all
three, but you don't need
to perform all three of
these tests if you don't
think there's consolidation.
If a patient comes in
because they have an ankle
injury and now you do
the heart and lung exam,
I wouldn't expect
you or I don't think
anybody would ever
expect you to do
bronchopony, egopony,
whispered pectorility.
But if there was a situation
where they came in and
they had shortness of breath
and a fever and now that
you think they have
consolidation, then it would
be expected that you would
do bronchopony, egophony,
and or whisper
textility. So
bronchopony, you're
going to be in a
seated position.
You're going to place a
stethoscope over the posterior
lung field and you're
going to ask the patient
to say, again say not
whisper, one, two, three, or
ninety-nine. You're going
to evaluate side to side,
two out of the four levels,
and normal should be
muffled in distinct sound
that you hear. And if you
hear it loud and clear,
that's usually abnormal.
Then we have eegophany.
Eegophany, think of the e,
right, and the patient is
going to say e. If you
hear them say a muffled e,
that's normal. If you hear
them say something that
sounds like an a, right,
that's going to be abnormal.
Whispered pectoralis key,
right, again, see this
position, stethoscope over
the posterior field, and now
you're going to ask the
patients to whisper. One, two,
three, or 99, and you're
going to evaluate side to
side, two out of the four
levels, and you should really
not be able to hear anything
at all. But if you hear
it loud and clear, that's
usually not a good sign.
That usually suggests
that there could be
consolidations. Right,
so again bronchopony,
egophony, and
whispers pectoralis.
Egophony right here
is two examples of
what potential
sound might be. I'm
getting rid of my pen,
and this is normal.
And that E does sound
like an E. Right,
this sound, E, is going
to sound like an A.
All right, so whispered
pectorilla key, again,
whispered numbers, one,
two, three, sounds soft,
is normal. If it's loud
and clear, it's abnormal.
So we will practice.
We'll just go through
some of the breath sounds.
So I'll play the first one.
So
that top left, that's the
tracheal breath sound.
So these are all normal
breath sounds that you
might hear. again normal
and abnormal it's going
to be abnormal but if
they're normal in a normal
position then that's their
normal exam all right
so those who said tracheal
that is tracheal this
is I'll let you guys
determine what this is if
you know what it is say
it out loud and you guys
are all correct right
that is your vesicular
breath down all right next
we're going to have your
bronchial breath
down and uh this
is your broncho vesicular
breath down uh so
for your convenience
I put these um answers
in your notes on the
bottom of the powerpoint
slide so if you don't
look at the slide
the actual powerpoint
it's in the notes on the
bottom you'll be able to
see it and these are all
going to be adventitious
slung sounds all right so
I know we might be a minute
over but I want to just
listen to these sounds
we're almost there that
is say it out loud
and you are all correct. All
right let's see the next one
and that is your
wheezing. Oh by the way
the first one I was
with crackles wheezing
and let's see what
the third one is.
That is your Ron Kai, and this
is the fourth one, alright?
And that is not good,
alright? That is your,
anybody knows what it is,
say it out loud, and you
are all correct. That
is your strider, right?
That is a sign of
respiratory distress, right?
So three very quick case
scenarios, right?
Very, very quick.
75-year-old male coming
in with a cough, started
six months ago, worsening
over the past week,
worse with any kind of
exertion, right? There's
some white sputum, but
most of the time it's dry.
Associated short of breath.
There's no fever. He
has a 50-year smoking
history of smoking one and a
half packs a day, and he
did quit six months ago.
This is his lungs down.
That's the lungs down,
so you can see that he is
wheezing as you're examining
him. Here we have a picture
of the x-ray, right?
The x-ray does look like
there's some flattened
diaphragm, right? There's some,
what is it?
The airway is midline, right?
The diaphragm is flattened,
right? You have an increased
AP diameter, right?
You know that he probably
has a barrel of chest,
right, when you look at
him on physical exam.
This is a classic
x-ray for a patient
with a diagnosis of
what do you all think.
Yes, I know you all said
COPD, I could hear you.
So the answer was
COPD. This is a patient
with COPD based on
the history, based on
the physical exam,
based on the imaging.
A 62-year-old female
coming in with a cough,
started two weeks to go,
dry in nature, work at
night, nasal congestion
and discharge, over-the
-counter allergies medication
with some improvement,
no smoking history, no
shortness of breath, no fever,
this is the physical exam,
lung sound,
and
that is a normal lung
sound, that's normal
vesicular sound, so sometimes
a physical exam can be
normal. You can have
normal lung sounds. You
don't always have to have
pathology. So that's a
normal lung sound. So this
case, you could probably
treat this patient for
an allergic rhinitis.
You want to do a full
head, eye, ear, or throat
exam. Look at the ears.
Look at the throat.
Especially the back of
the throat. You're looking
for any kind of cobblestoning
or post-nasal drip.
And third and final case,
you have an 18-year-old
female with a cough.
Started about 24 hours ago.
Now we have a fever and
now we have phlegm, right?
So we're thinking, okay,
maybe it's an infection.
Worsening, shortness of breath.
Over-the-counter medication
with no relief. Physical
exam is going to have the
following lung sound. You
also have abnormal lung
sound over the right middle
lobe, right? So maybe you have
normal breath sound that's
in an abnormal place that's
over the middle lobe,
in addition Listen to the
crackles that we just heard.
Now you have an idea that
because you hear
it in the front,
you have an idea that on
the right side, you're
thinking that it's potentially
in the right middle
lobe, you send them for
an x-ray and just confirm
that it's a pneumonia
on the right middle lobe
and you treat this patient for
a pneumonia with antibiotics.
And the fourth and final
case, you have a two
-year-old male with a
cluff, started about
five days ago. It's
an upper respiratory
infection, and it's
worsening over the 24 hours.
Mom says that he sounds like a
seal, very
uncomfortable at night.
This is the one sound.
All right, so you get an
x-ray, and you see people
sign so that's why we
bring up the pen and so we
have people sign right because
we can kind of see that
right in here right and
if you don't know what
it is you go on Google and
you type in what is this
people and this is a picture
that you might see and
you can kind of see the
similarity there and that
is an example of croup or
laryngotracheobronchitis
Again, this is a neck x
-ray that we wanted to order
because this is what we were
thinking that it might be.
So those are your
clinical scenarios.
Summary slide, knowing
the anatomy is going
to help you with the
physical exam. Allow the
history and the physical
exam and any other
testing that you do,
put them all together
to come up with the
differential diagnosis.
Understanding
abnormal physical exam
finding will lead you
to your diagnosis.
And so here are some
of the references.
The textbook did get updated
to 2023, so if you have
any questions, by all
means, please let me know.
Here's an extra feedback
form, and good luck
to you all on upcoming
exams, and good luck on
upcoming rotations, in
case I don't get to see
you before then, and
thank you for joining me.
Have a great evening, or
morning, or whatever
it might be.
Take care.